[music]
>> Welcome to this 2026 release wave one
launch edition of Business Central. This
session is super cool and I'm very
excited because I've been waiting
for us to present this ever since I
started in Microsoft 10 years ago. It's
about enhanced index management. My name
is Kenny Pontoppidan. I work on the
product team and with me I have Mass.
My name is Mass Gram. I'm one of the
engineers in the server team and I was
one of the people who made this feature
and happy to show this off.
Awesome.
Let's uh
just talk a little bit about why we did
this. So, there are at least three
things that are relevant here. First is
that you can now analyze your data
performance and based on that you can
make it faster um and maybe also save
something on your storage.
We just have two demos, but they are
really important things. First is that
you can use the table data information
management
page to go and see your index structure.
Based on that you can then turn indexes
on and off. So, let's let's start with a
demo on uh how this new page what it
does, what you can use it for. So, Mass
take that away. Thank you, Kenny.
So, we're starting off on a page that
many of you already know. It's the table
information page where you can see size,
storage usage on a per company, per
table basis. However, we have introduced
something new.
Now, you'll be able to drill down using
this little feature here.
And there you can now see information
again on a per table, per company, but
you can now see per index information.
So,
we can for example go and take a look at
the index size for each index where we
were previously only able to see it on a
aggregated view on the entire table.
We can also see more advanced
information about how the index is being
used in the product. This will allow
very advanced administrators or
developers to make decisions about
indexes their disabling or creation.
And what about the index details down
there? What what does that show? So,
>> See more or Yeah, of course. So, if you
scroll down a little bit here, you will
be able to see which fields are in the
index and which fields are included in
the index. Oh, nice. Two different
things here, included fields in the
index.
Very technical details there.
So, for someone who's tuning using
indexes, this is super important because
it allows them directly without going to
the source code to
to to see whether this index is covering
or not based on what type of query.
Super cool. Let's let's go to the other
feature, which is turning things on and
off. Back in the days where Business
Central was called Dynamics NAV, uh
there was a tool called C/SIDE for
developing and interacting with Business
Central. And in that tool C/SIDE, it it
was possible
simply to turn indexes on and off. Now,
we have moved from C/SIDE to the AL
language and other experiences and
along the way, I can think of 3 years
ago, we introduced the way the ability
in AL to be able to turn indexes on and
off
um in in in the base app and in your own
code. However,
um
the full kind of C/SIDE experience
is coming now where you can now turn
indexes on and off directly in the
client.
Let's see a demo of that, Mass.
>> Yeah. Thank you, Kenny. So, we stay on
the same page where we see the indexes
and we're able to interact with them.
Now, some indexes you can turn off and
on, while some you cannot. If we start
here with the system ID, it is defined
as being unique. It would be a
semantically different experience if you
turned it off. So, we do disallow
certain, but some of them you can turn
on or turn off. So, if you for example
take here key 11, we can now see there's
a bit more interesting fields down here.
Let's take a look what happens when we
turn the index off.
Surprisingly, not a lot in the UI, but
behind the scenes in SQL, the index will
now be turned off. You can also see that
there's no longer any seek scans,
lookups, updates information because the
index simply does not exist in SQL
anymore.
Why do we want to do that? Well, it of
course saves some storage on the
database, but it is also cheaper to now
update the table cuz we no longer have
to alter that one.
But we cannot of course just turn it
off. We can also turn it on. So, let's
take another example index here. We have
key four.
Key four
is an index that at least in this
version of the product is created as
disabled.
So, enabled equals false. Those indices
you have normally not been able to turn
on, but you can now turn them on here.
We say here they will be in queued and
turned on in the subsequent maintenance
window overnight depending on local
time.
I have a local version of it and in
Docker running locally or on prem, that
will happen immediately, but in SaaS
over the next maintenance window.
What this will enable is a feature we
have heard from many and that is you can
now per company make indices that will
be useful for certain companies. They
might only enable some functionality in
some part in some companies.
And other companies might not want to
have the cost, extra storage, extra time
when you update them.
So, only for some of companies you now
turn this index on.
Awesome. Thanks a lot for that, Mass.
And I have I think this is a great
feature because
uh also because when we develop the base
app, we are trying to guess the types of
indexes that would make sense, but we
don't necessarily know the data
distribution for any company out there.
So, the only thing we can do in the base
app is making it wrong for most
customers. With this, we can also ship
and you can do that in your apps. You
can ship indexes that could be useful,
but you could also ship some that are by
default turned off and and based on the
usage of the system, the administrator
can can then turn things on. So, good
stuff.
As
everything related to life cycle, we
have telemetry and
the telemetry we have when you enable
or turn indexes on and off from AL have
had life cycle events for years. Now, we
have the runtime capability, so we have
a new events for that.
LC 63 and 64. And um
all of that is of course documented here
on the ak.ms/bctelemetry.
So, you can if you want to monitor that
uh telemetry signal and build some
reporting on that, uh it's it's all the
the schema is
is documented there.
All right, let's it's time to wrap up
and uh we have
like a summary slides here on on
everything we talked about, but Mass, is
there kind of one thing you want to
highlight from this?
Yeah, so I want to highlight what I
think is a new ability that we haven't
had since C/SIDE and that is the ability
to create an index with enabled false
and then activate that selectively for
some companies.
This is something that you could do back
in the C/SIDE time. I imagine this will
really enable some functional areas to
be sped up by certain indexes. A lot of
indexes are created now and they are
actually meant for maybe one
functionality, but not everyone uses
that one functionality. So, I think this
is a great ability and this is where I
imagine we will see some more indexes
that are defined for just that thing
without having that huge storage impact
and time impact when
inserting in modifying data in SQL.
Awesome.
If you want to learn more, your friend
is ak.ms/bcdeveloper.
That takes you to the developer
documentation.
And here
you you simply go to the
documentation for keys or for indexes um
whether there would be dedicated
articles or or in in this article is to
be decided. Uh we don't know that at the
recording, but this is where you find
all of what you need to know.
If this is your thing, you might have
other
sessions that could be for you. So,
there's one especially the server and
database related related session that
goes into other things around the
runtime. Go check that out. There will
be a link in the description for it.
And with that, you can stay on the video
and if you don't know the general
Business Central resources, for now,
Mass and I are done.
Thank you so much for what what watching
and have a great launch edition.
Bye. Bye.
We have compiled a number of general
resources that we believe are key both
for partners, but also Business Central
customers. Most Some of these are
partner, some of them are also for
customers. So, the first one is
called aka.ms/bcall.
This is a partner resource for that
contains lists of every other aka link
that is needed for you to understand
anything about both the business Central
product, but also processes around it.
We call these aka links because they're
called aka.ms and then for forward slash
something. And with business Central
links we all always prefix with BC and
then something.
The next one is our partner network
social media for for business Central
partners Viva Viva Engage. So,
aka.ms/bcvivaengage
is where you go and interact with other
partners. It's not open for customers.
So, this is where you can ask questions,
interact with the product group,
interact with with with each other
in a in a closed network.
Second link The third link is for both
partners and customers we are called
office hours. So, office hours is
something we do once or twice a month
from the product group engaging with the
community about new features or things
we want to discuss. aka.ms/bcofficehours
is the is the place where you go to find
out about upcoming events.
These are recorded. I believe the
recordings are available only to
partners, but the live events are
available to customers as well.
Fourth link is YouTube our YouTube
channel. I'll talk about that
in the next slide and LinkedIn in the
next slide.
And then finally for for Microsoft
partners
the BC's aka.ms/bcpartnerportal
is where you get
a lot of the resources as a partner such
as compete decks,
pitch decks and a lot of other
resources.
For LinkedIn, this is our product
group's LinkedIn profile. We have 30k or
more followers. So, both partners and
customers. This is the place where we
from the product group put in news and
small bits of information outside the
official channel. So,
follow us on LinkedIn to learn what's
happening right now
in in this in the around the product.
Um, and then
also on our YouTube channel where this
is why you're probably watching this
aka.ms/bcyoutube.
We put in not only these launch editions
twice a year, but also
co-pilot and AI video shorts, tips and
tricks, technical deep dives, under the
hood.
We even have this what's cooking where
we put little nuggets of of videos out
for new features that are even coming in
the YouTube channel before
they're coming in the release notes. So,
watch
and maybe
bookmark us on YouTube. And also notice
all the playlists. So,
the content is also organized in areas,
not only all the videos. So, if you have
an area that has special interest such
as analytics,
you can find a an
a playlist and kind of see all the
content related to that.
And that's it. That is truly it. We
won't
There would be no more. So, thank you
for watching all the way to the end.
And again, have a great day. Thank you.